Guide to the David Stidolph Papers 1941-1997
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
David Stidolph Papers
1941-1997
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Cage 798
Stidolph, David Leslie, 1923-2004
2.25 Linear feet of shelf space 3 Boxes
Primarily correspondence and other papers related to David Stidolph's personal and professional relationship with his friend, author John McCallum, along with a small amount of material related to Stidolph's professional activities in creative marketing and communications.
David Leslie Stidolph (1923-2004) was a pioneer in creative marketing for fresh produce from the 1950s to the 1990s. He received his B.A. from the University of Idaho in 1947, and his M.A. from Washington State University in 1948. He served as a Perishable Air-Cargo Consultant for Transworld Airlines, which introduced air transport of fresh fruit and vegetables. In 1982, he joined Mann Packing, a large agribusiness enterprise based in Salinas, California, first working as the Director of Food Service and then as Director of Creative Marketing. Recognized as an innovator in branding and developing fresh portions in produce for mass-marketing, he was known in agribusiness as the "father of the broccoli florette." In 1993, he was named "Produce Man of All Seasons" by the United Fresh Fruit and Vegetable Association.
John Dennis McCallum (1924-1988), whose correspondence with Stidolph comprises much of this collection, was Stidolph's classmate at Washington State College in the 1940s. He was a sportswriter, columnist, and author of nonfiction books. McCallum received his M.A. from Washington State University in 1947. He published hundreds of articles and over thirty books, including Pac-10 Football: The Rose Bowl Conference (1982), several other major football conference histories, The Tiger Wore Spikes (a biography of Ty Cobb, 1956), Everest Diary (1966), and Crime Doctor (1978).
The bulk of the material in this collection consists of correspondence between David Stidolph and author John McCallum, his friend and classmate from Washington State University in the late 1940s. The collection also includes a small amount of biographical material about Stidolph, as well as materials related to his creative marketing and communications work, particularly during his agribusiness career at Mann Packing.
Series 1: John McCallum files, circa 1940s-1995. This series comprises the bulk of the collection, and includes correspondence between Stidolph and McCallum (mostly incoming), notes and correspondence with others about McCallum, photographs, and Stidolph's files on one of McCallum's books, PAC-10 Football: the Rose Bowl Conference (Seattle: The Writing Works, 1982). Stidolph's extensive correspondence with McCallum covers personal and professional matters, reflecting their close friendship. They often wrote about their professional achievements, encouraging each other in their endeavors, but also sustaining an enduring friendly competition.
Series 2: Personal and professional papers, 1941-1997. Most of the material in this series relates to Stidolph's work in creative marketing and communications, along with a small amount of personal material.
This collection is arranged in two series. Series 1 is arranged in chronological order.
This collection is open and available for research use.
David Stidolph donated these papers to the Washington State University Libraries between 1991 and 1993 (MS 1991-36, MS 1991-40, MS 1993-24).
Bound volume of Radio Releases--Athletic News Service, Washington State College, January 4, 1949-November 15, 1949 (transferred to WSU 31).
Removed for separate cataloging: The Coit Fishing Pole Club Beginner's Book of Fishing, by John McCallum and David Stidolph (Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Prentice-Hall, 1958). Call number: SH441 M28 1958.
John Dennis McCallum Manuscripts, 1956-1960 (Cage 64)
John Dennis McCallum Papers, circa 1920-1988 (Cage 799)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Stidolph, David Leslie, 1923-2004 -- Archives; McCallum, John Dennis, 1924-1988
Sportswriters -- United States -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Manuscripts
Sports and Recreation; Literature
- Series 1: John McCallum files, circa 1940s-1995
  - McCallum correspondence, 1960-1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - McCallum correspondence, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - McCallum correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - McCallum correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - McCallum correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - McCallum correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - McCallum correspondence, 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - McCallum correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - McCallum correspondence, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stidolph notes and correspondence with others about McCallum, 1988-1991; McCallum miscellaneous items, 1955-1970s, 1955-1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings by and about McCallum; Janice Smith paper on McCallum; McCallum publicity, 1957-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of McCallum (5 items), circa 1940s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - McCallum's book, PAC-10 Football: page proofs with Stidolph's notes, circa 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - McCallum's book, PAC-10 Football: correspondence about the project, promotion, Stidolph contribution (poem), 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Stidolph's notes for an unfinished poem for McCallum's forthcoming SEC Conference football book, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series 2: Personal and professional papers, 1941-1997
  - Stidolph curriculum vitae, circa 1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Stidolph publicity, work samples, and biographical information (includes some correspondence with Washington State University), 1973-1997 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Ernest Lasolino (correspondence and notes), 1941-1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1995 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous items, circa 1956-1989 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Broccoli marketing materials (includes audio recording, "Broccoli-Wokly Two-Step," on audiocassette), circa 1983-1990 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Video recordings (3 items, VHS cassettes): Mann Packing Co., "Sunny Shores," circa 1961-1962, produced by David Stidolph; "Salinas Strawberries," Spanish version, undated; "The Packer Man of the Year," United Fresh Fruit and Vegetable Association, San Diego, 1993, 1961-1993 (Box 3, Folder 23)